A Guide to John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Part Four: Printed Matter from Magazines, Newspapers, and Books (Box 9)
  - "SCHOOLS TO HONOR POE," unsigned; "HEARD POE READ'RAVEN'," unsigned, 1909 ante January 19.; [963]; 3/4 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    First article outlines plans to celebrate the centennial of Poe's birth in Baltimore schools. The second article presents the recollections of Dr. Basil L. Gildersleeve of Johns Hopkins University.
  - "GOVERNOR FOR POE DAY," unsigned, 1909 ante January 19.; [964]; 1/2 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun? (Box 17)
    Austin L. Crothers, Governor of Maryland, promotes exercises marking Poe centennial.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE, " by Leopold Katscher, 1909 January 19.; [965]; 6 1/2 columns clipped from the Hannoverscher Courier (Box 17)
    In German. On the Poe centennial.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE. A GENIUS OF THE SHADOWS," unsigned, 1909 January 19.; [966]; 1 column clipped from the Birmingham Daily Mail (Box 17)
    Centennial tribute.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE. ZU SEINEM HUNERTSTEN GEBURTSTAG" [" EDGAR ALLAN POE ON HIS HUNDREDTH BIRTHDAY"], by Dr. G. Markus, 1909 January 19, 20, 21.; [967]; Parts I, II, III clipped from Neue Zuercher Zeitung (Box 17)
  - "NEL CENTENARIO DI EDGAR ALLAN POE, " by Ulisse Ortensi, 1909 January 20.; [968]; 2 columns clipped from La Tribuna (Box 17)
    In Italian.
  - "POE'S FAME SECURE," unsigned, 1909 January 20.; [969]; 6 columns clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    Descriptions of Poe centennial celebrations in Baltimore, West Point, New York, Boston, Providence, Annapolis, and Charlottesville.
  - NEWSPAPER AND MAGAZINE ARTICLES IN HONOR OF THE POE CENTENNIAL CELEBRATIONS IN FRANCE, unsigned, 1909 January 20.; [970]; Paragraph clipped from the Times (London) (Box 17)
  - "LE CENTENAIRE D' EDGAR POE, " by Nol Clerban, 1909 January 20, 21.; [971]; 6 1/4 columns clipped from Les Nouvelles (Box 17)
  - " EDGAR POE ET SES AMIS," by John H. Ingram, 1909 January 21.; [972]; 4 columns clipped from Gazette de France (Box 17)
    In French. An abridgment of Ingram's article, " Edgar Poe and Some of His Friends," the Bookman (London), January 1909, as it has been translated into French by Henri D. Davray for Le Mercure de France.
  - "POE AND MRS. WHITMAN," letter to the Editor by John H. Ingram, 1909 January 30.; [973]; 1/2 column clipped from the New York Tribune (Box 17)
    Ingram protests the wording of Professor Harrison's article in the Century Magazine for January ( James A. Harrison and Charlotte F. Dailey, "Poe and Mrs. Whitman --New Light on a Romantic Episode") and promises a revised and enlarged version of his own Edgar Allan Poe: His Life, Letters and Opinions. Appended to this is a letter from Richard Watson Gilder, editor of the Century Magazine, to the Editor of the Tribune in which he writes that Ingram was responding to copies of Professor Harrison's article that differed from the final printed version.
  - THE POE CENTENNIAL, unsigned, 1909 January 31.; [974]; 1 column clipped from the Statesman (Box 17)
    Centennial tribute. Notes that Richmond, VA, objected to the erection of a statue in Poe's memory on grounds of his personal character.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE, " an address by Professor John Prentiss Poe, 1909 January.; [975]; Pp. 1-6 clipped from Old Maryland, IV-V (December 1908-January 1909) (Box 17)
    Professor Poe, Dean of the Faculty of Law at the University of Maryland, delivered this address at the Poe centennial celebration held in Baltimore on 19 January. Old Maryland was a publication of the University of Maryland.
  - " EDGAR POE AND SOME OF HIS FRIENDS," by John H. Ingram (pp. 167-173); "THE LIFE-STORY OF EDGAR ALLAN POE, " by Mary Bradford Whiting (pp. 173-181), 1909 January.; [976]; The Bookman (London): Edgar Allan Poe Centenary Number, XXXV (Box 17)
    Includes pictures of Poe, John Allan, Frances Allan, Virginia Poe, John Neal, William Clemm, Jr., Maria Clemm, William Gowans, Judge Neilson Poe, Frances Sargent Osgood, Sarah Helen Whitman, Marie Louise Shew Houghton, Sarah Elmira Royster Shelton, John P. Kennedy.
  - "POE'S COTTAGE AT FORDHAM, " by Reverend John B. Tabb (p. 428); "POE AND SECRET WRITING," by Firmin Dredd (pp. 450-451); " EDGAR ALLAN POE'S LOST POEM'THE BEAUTIFUL PHYSICIAN'," by John H. Ingram (pp. 452-454); " EDGAR ALLAN POE IN SOCIETY," by Eugene L. Didier (pp. 455-460), 1909 January.; [977]; The Bookman (New York), XXVIII (Box 17)
  - "POE," by William C. Brownell, 1909 January.; [978]; Scribner's Magazine, XLV,69-84 (Box 17)
  - " EDGAR POE. L'OEUVRE ET LA METHODE," by M. D. Calvocoressi, 1909 January.; [979]; Pp. 111-113 clipped from L'Opinion (Box 17)
  - "POE," by George L. Knapp, 1909 January.; [980]; Pp. 74-81 clipped from Lippincott's Magazine (Box 17)
    A critical estimate that finds Poe at the climax of his powers in his romances.
  - " EDGAR ALLEN [sic] POE, " by F. C. Owlett, 1909 January.; [981]; Pp. 231-234 clipped from the Bibliophile (Box 17)
    Biographical-critical.
  - "A CAUSERIE: EDGAR ALLAN POE, " by J. Macartney Wilson, 1909 January.; [982]; 2 columns clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 17)
    Laudatory article on Poe and on Ingram's four-volume edition of his works.
  - REVIEW OF SOME POEMS OF EDGAR ALLAN POE. WITH DRAWINGS BY JAMES GUTHRIE, unsigned review, 1909 January.; [983]; 1/4 column clipped from an unidentified magazine (Box 17)
  - SURVEY OF THE CENTENARIES TO BE OBSERVED IN 1909, by Alan Northman, 1909 ca. January.; [984]; 2 columns clipped from the Sunday School Chronicle and Christian Outlook (London) (Box 17)
    Comments on Poe's place in literature and on the controversy about variations in the last line of "Annabel Lee" and recalls the story of Emerson's having called Poe "the jingle man."
  - " EDGAR POE. SES BIOGRAPHERS, SES DITEURS, SES CRITIQUES," by M. D. Calvocoressi, 1909 February 1.; [985]; Mercury de France, LXXVII, 385-403 (Box 17)
    Heavily and angrily annotated by Ingram, who wrote the editor that the article contained statements prejudicial to the honor of Poe and to himself.
  - "THE POE CENTENARY DINNER," unsigned, 1909 February 25.; [986]; 1/4 column clipped from the Times (London) (Box 17)
    The Authors' Club has arranged a dinner honoring Poe's centennial to be held in the Whitehall Rooms of the Hotel Metropole. Sir Arthur Conan Doyle is the Chairman, and Ingram is to be a guest.
  - "MORE ROMANCES ABOUT POE," letter to the Editor by John H. Ingram, 1909 February 28.; [987]; 1/3 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    Ingram's letter, dated 1 January 1909, protests the wording used in the James A. Harrison and Charlotte F. Dailey article ("Poe and Mrs. Whitman --New Light on a Romantic Episode," Century Magazine). A note from "H" to the Editor, prefacing Ingram's letter, states that Ingram particularly wanted this protest printed in a Baltimore paper.
  - "POE, THE WEIRD GENIUS," by Elisabeth Ellicott Poe, 1909 February.; [988]; Pp. 243-252 clipped from Cosmopolitan Magazine, XLVI (Box 17)
  - CONTROVERSY OVER POE'S BIRTHPLACE, unsigned, 1909 ca. February.; [989]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 17)
    Was it Boston or Baltimore ?
  - "THE POE CENTENARY," unsigned, 1909 March 2.; [990]; 2 1/2 columns clipped from the Times (London) (Box 17)
    Account of the dinner honoring Poe's centennial held by the Authors' Club. Quotes from speeches by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle and Whitelaw Reid.
  - "HONORS POE'S MEMORY," unsigned, 1909 March 2.; [991]; 1/2 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    Sir Arthur Conan Doyle presided at a dinner given by the London Authors' Club honoring Poe's centennial.
  - "UN AMOUR D' EDGAR POE, " by Gabriel Mourey, 1909 March 6.; [992]; Revue Beleue, No. 10, pp. 307-311 (Box 17)
    In French. Survey of Poe's relationship with Sarah Helen Whitman.
  - "POE'S INDEBTEDNESS TO BYRON," letter to the Editor by Killis Campbell, 1909 March 11.; [993]; 4 columns clipped from the Nation, LXXXVIII, 248-249 (Box 17)
  - "HAS POE MANUSCRIPT," unsigned, 1909 March 15.; [994]; 3/4 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    Eugene L. Didier offers the MS. of "Morella" for sale. Professor Henry E. Shepherd has a piece of wood from Poe's original coffin.
  - "POE'S LOVE LETTERS," unsigned, 1909 March 21.; [995]; 3/4 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    Review of The Last Letters of Edgar Allan Poe to Sarah Helen Whitman, edited by James A. Harrison.
  - "PROF. HARRISON RESIGNS," unsigned, 1909 March 23.; [996]; 1/2 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    James A. Harrison has resigned from his chair at the University of Virginia and will be succeeded by Professor Charles Alphonso Smith.
  - "VARIATIONS IN EDGAR POE'S POETRY," by John H. Ingram, 1909 May.; [997]; Bibliophile, III, 128-136 (Box 17)
    A study of variations in Poe's poetry as he revised it.
  - GEORGE FRANCIS ZIMMER SINGS POE'S "EL DORADO," unsigned, 1909 June 15.; [998]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified Baltimore newspaper (Box 17)
    Mr. Zimmer performed at a celebration in Petersburg, VA.
  - " EUGENE L. DIDIER AND THE AUTHOR OF'THE RAVEN'," unsigned, 1909 June 27.; [999]; 1 1/2 columns clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 17)
    Favorable review of Didier's The Poe Cult, and Other Poe Papers.
  - "POE AND THE `SOUTHERN LITERARY MESSENGER' IN 1837," letter to the Editor by Killis Campbell, 1909 July 1.; [1000]; 3 columns clipped from the Nation (Box 18)
    Campbell prints for the first time Poe's letter to Sarah Josepha Hale, dated 20 October 1837 [text printed in Letters, I, 105-106], to prove that Poe was again in Richmond and helping edit the Southern Literary Messenger in 1837. Poe, however, misdated the letter: it should have been 1836.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE'S'CHILD WIFE'," by Josephine Poe January, 1909 October.; [1001]; Pp. 894-896 clipped from the Century Magazine (Box 18)
    Prints an unpublished thirteen-line acrostic written by Virginia Poe to her husband in 1846.
  - "BIBLIOGRAPHICAL NOTES ON POE -- I," by Killis Campbell, 1909 December 23.; [1002]; 5 columns clipped from the Nation, pp. 623-624 (Box 18)
    Campbell adds to the bibliography of Poe's criticisms --Burton's Gentleman's Magazine, Graham's Magazine, the Weekly Mirror, the Broadway Journal, and the Democratic Review.
  - "BIBLIOGRAPHICAL NOTES ON POE -- II," by Killis Campbell, 1909 December 30.; [1003]; 3 columns clipped from the Nation, pp. 647-648 (Box 18)
    Having found a file of the Flag of Our Union for 1849 in the Library of Congress, Campbell identifies the Poe tales and poems published there.
  - "MR. J. P. MORGAN'S PURCHASE," unsigned, 1909 December.; [1004]; 1/5 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    J. P. Morgan paid $3,800 for MSS. of "The Murders in the Rue Morgue" and "The Man That Was Used Up."
  - "POE AND COLERIDGE," by Henry Marvin Belden, 1910 January 6.; [1005]; 1/2 column clipped from the Nation, XC, 11 (Box 18)
    "Coleridge had preceded Schlegel as Poe's teacher."
  - "NOT WORRYING," unsigned, 1910 March 30.; [1006]; Paragraph clipped from the Baltimore Sun, reprinted from the Louisville Courier-Journal (Box 18)
    Poe's tales and verses testify to the genius of Poe more than admission to the Hall of Fame.
  - "POE DOCUMENTS IN THE LIBRARY OF CONGRESS, " by Killis Campbell, 1910 April.; [1007]; Pp. 127-128 clipped from Modern Language Notes, XXV (Box 18)
    Describes four letters and four bills pertaining to Poe that have not been used by his biographers.
  - JAMES H. WHITTY'S THE COMPLETE POEMS OF EDGAR ALLAN POE SCHEDULED FOR AUTUMN PUBLICATION; A FILE OF FLAG OF OUR UNION HAS BEEN DISCOVERED, unsigned notice, 1910 September.; [1008]; P. 234 clipped from the Bookman (London) (Box 18)
  - "SOME NEW POE POEMS," unsigned, 1910 October 16.; [1009]; 1 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    "New forms" of "A Valentine," "For Annie," and "To My Mother" have been discovered in Flag of Our Union.
  - "'THE NEW POE POEMS' -- MR. DIDIER HAS A FEW THINGS TO SAY OF THE DISCOVERY," letter to the Editor by Eugene L. Didier, 1910 October 18.; [1010]; 1/3 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    Didier criticizes James A. Harrison for his "eagerness" to publish every minute change in Poe's poetry.
  - "POE IS FAMOUS AT LAST," unsigned, 1910 October 23.; [1011]; 1/2 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    With two undated short newsclippings from the Sun: "Poe Has Come into His Own" and "Admitted"; a large cartoon showing Uncle Sam carrying a bust of Poe into the Hall of Fame. Poe is one of eleven persons elected to the Hall of Fame. Fifty-five votes were needed; he received sixty-nine.
  - "MS. OF POE'S'MORELLA'," unsigned, 1910.; [1012]; 1/5 column clipped from the New York Sun (Box 18)
    The "original first draft" of Poe's "Morella" is to be sold at an auction at Anderson's Gallery.
  - "DR. J. A. HARRISON DEAD," unsigned, 1911 January 31.; [1013]; 2/3 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    Professor Harrison died in Charlottesville on 31 January and is to be buried in Lexington, VA.
  - "TAUGHT AT CATONSVILLE, " unsigned, 1911 February 2.; [1014]; 1/3 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    Didier notes that he criticized Professor James A. Harrison's edition of Poe's Works as being "too voluminous."
  - "A NEW TEXT OF POE'S POEMS," by Killis Campbell, 1911 July 1.; [1015]; Pp. 13-14 clipped from the Dial, LI, pp. 13-14 (Box 18)
    Politely critical review of James H. Whitty's The Complete Poems of Edgar Allan Poe.
  - "RARE TREASURE," unsigned, 1911 January 12.; [1016]; 1/2 column clipped from the Philadelphia Ledger (Box 18)
    Surveys Poe's contributions to the Columbia Spy.
  - "A LOVER OF EDGAR ALLAN POE AND A POET HIMSELF," unsigned, 1911 March 10.; [1017]; 1/2 p. clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    A profile of Orrin C. Painter, including a photograph of him, a sketch of the gateway he erected to Poe's tomb, and a selection from Painter's poetry.
  - "SOME UNPUBLISHED DOCUMENTS RELATING TO POE'S EARLY YEARS," by Killis Campbell, 1911 April.; [1018]; Reprint from the Sewanee Review, XX, 201-212 (Box 18)
    Discoveries in the Ellis-Allan Papers in the Library of Congress: letters from Elizabeth Poe, Baltimore, to Mrs. John Allan, Richmond; John Allan's correspondence; bills from the University of Virginia.
  - POE MSS. AND DOCUMENTS FOUND, unsigned, 1911 ante June 15.; [1019]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified English newspaper (Box 18)
    Reports that John Quincy Adams has discovered a box of mss. and printed matter relating to Poe and his associates. According to Doris V. Falk, the John Quincy Adams mentioned was the nephew of Thomas Holley Chivers and he did have custody of this box of papers. He published articles about them in the Atlanta Constitution in March of 1888 (from which this 1912 paragraph was copied almost verbatim), and again in 1897. The papers remained in the Adams family until some were bought by the Huntington Library and others by the Duke University Library. Mentions: Professor George Bush, Professor Gierlow, Thomas Holley Chivers, Maria Clemm, Jane Ermina Locke, Sarah Elmira Royster Shelton, William Gilmore Simms, Sarah Helen Whitman, N. P. Willis.
  - "GRAVE OF POE'S MOTHER FOUND," unsigned, 1911 November 1.; [1020]; 1/2 column clipped from the Richmond Times Dispatch (Box 18)
    Samuel P. Cowardin, Jr., and The Raven Society of the University of Virginia have succeeded in identifying the approximate location of the grave of Elizabeth Arnold Poe in Old St. John's Churchyard, Richmond.
  - " STEPHANE MALLARME, " unsigned, 1913 May 1.; [1021]; 2 columns clipped from the Times Literary Supplement (Box 18)
    Reviews of Mallarme's Posies and of La Posie de Stephane Mallarme. tude Littraire, by Albert Thibaudet.
  - "POE AND DICKENS: A MYSTERY CLEARED UP," letter to the Editor by "Claudius Clear", 1913 June 26.; [1022]; 4 columns clipped from the British Weekly (Box 18)
    Declares that Poe was mistaken in all essentials in his famous forecast of the plot of Dickens' Barnaby Rudge.
  - "MISS AMELIA F. POE, " unsigned, 1913 ca. March 20.; [1023]; 1/5 column clipped from the Baltimore Sun (Box 18)
    Obituary of Amelia F. Poe, who died in Baltimore at the age of eighty-one.
  - "EARLY STOKE NEWINGTON, " unsigned, 1915 March 20.; [1024]; 1 1/2 columns clipped from the Hackney Record (Box 18)
    Summary of a lecture on Poe and Stoke Newington given by Lewis Chase, Ph.D., including suggestion that Poe may have heard the local "Tale of the Dead Hand."
  - "NEW POE POEMS AND MANUSCRIPTS FOUND," by James H. Whitty, 1915 November 21.; [1025]; Full page clipped from the Baltimore Sunday American (Box 18)
    Describes Whitty's discoveries concerning Poe in the Ellis-Allan Papers in the Library of Congress. Whitty attributes newly found verses to Poe: "Ally Croaker," "Burial of Sir John Moore," "The Divine Right of Kings," "Elizabeth," "Extracts from Byron's Dream," "Life's Vital Stream," "Soldier's Burial," and "Stanzas."
  - "THE PASSING OF POE'S ENGLISH BIOGRAPHER," by James H. Whitty, 1916 June 22.; [1026]; 1 column clipped from the Dial, p. 15 (Box 18)
    John Henry Ingram died at Brighton, England, 12 February 1916.
  - "INGRAM -- DISCOURAGER OF POE BIOGRAPHIES," by Caroline Ticknor (pp. 8-14); " EDGAR ALLAN POE IN ENGLAND AND SCOTLAND, " by James H. Whitty (pp.14-21), 1916 September.; [1027]; Front cover and pp. 7-21 clipped from the Bookman (New York) (Box 18)
    Obituary of Ingram and a lengthy account of his personality and his obsession with all things concerning Poe.
  - "POE'S GUARDIAN ANGEL," unsigned, n.d..; [1028]; 1 1/2 columns clipped from the Critic (Box 18)
    A reprint of a portion of Nathaniel Parker Willis' letter about Maria Clemm.
  - " EDGAR POE AND HIS POETRY," unsigned, [1029]; 1 1/2 columns clipped from the Brighton Herald. A fragment? (Box 18)
    A brief introduction to Poe's life, reputation, and poetry.
  - " EDGAR A. POE'S DEATH," unsigned, n.d..; [1030]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 18)
    Poe's death followed a beating by ruffians in Baltimore after he had gotten drunk with old friends from West Point.
  - POE THE GRANDSON OF BENEDICT ARNOLD, unsigned, [1031]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 18)
    Poe's mother, Elizabeth Arnold, was the natural daughter of the traitor.
  - "ODE -- TO EDGAR ALLAN POE, " by Frederick Herbert Trench, n.d..; [1032]; 4-page pamphlet. (Box 18)
  - " EDGAR POE'S GRAVE," by William Henry Babcock, n.d..; [1033]; 2 7-line stanzas clipped from an unidentified publication (Box 18)
  - "DR. PORTEOUS," unsigned, n.d..; [1034]; 1/4 column clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 18)
    Dr. George B. Porteous of London lectures in Brooklyn on genius and reads "The Raven" and "Annabel Lee": "The great London Preacher telling the Brooklynites what he knows about genius --reading Poe's'Raven'."
  - ILLUSTRATED REPRINT OF "THE RAVEN", n.d..; [1035]; Pp. 215-218 clipped from an unidentified magazine (Box 18)
  - "LENORE," unsigned, n.d..; [1036]; Pp. 1-3 clipped from Our Christmas Prize, published in London (Box 18)
    A romantic tale based upon Poe's supposed "lost Lenore."
  - "OLD TIME AMUSEMENTS AND LECTURING IN BOSTON, " unsigned, [1037]; 1/3 column clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 18)
    Reminiscences of Poe's Boston lecture in 1845.
  - "A BLACK BIRD THAT COULD SING BUT WOULDN'T SING," unsigned, n.d..; [1038]; 14 7-line stanzas clipped from an unidentified newspaper, reprinted from the Augusta Chronicle and Sentinel (Box 18)
    A parody of "The Raven."
  - "THE ART OF EDGAR ALLAN POE, " unsigned, n.d..; [1039]; 1/4 column clipped from an unidentified English newspaper (Box 18)
    In a lecture before the Portsmouth Literary and Scientific Society, G. F. Good said that Poe was the most self-centered egotist the world has seen since Alexander. Members of the Society decided they are profoundly thankful Poe is not one of their English poets.
  - "A BOOK WORTH READING," unsigned, n.d..; [1040]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified Baltimore newspaper (Box 18)
    In his essay "Poe as a Story-Writer" in Studies in Several Literatures, Harry Thurston Peck expresses appreciation for the "intellectuality" Poe "displayed in his'Eureka'."
  - "HINE'S PORTRAIT OWNED BY DR. GEO. REULING," unsigned, n.d..; [1041]; Clipping from an unidentified Baltimore newspaper. A fragment (Box 18)
    Article reproduces the portrait of Poe painted by Charles Hine in 1848.
  - REVIEW OF A JULES VERNE BOOK, unsigned, n.d..; [1042]; Fragment of a paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 18)
    Reviewer believes that Verne's method of handling certain incidents resembles Poe's method in "A Descent into the Maelstrom."
  - MURDER OF MARY ROGERS, unsigned, n.d..; [1043]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 18)
    Recalls that the murder of Mary Rogers, the subject of Poe's "The Mystery of Marie Roget," has never been solved.
  - "MR. POE GUEST OF HONOR," unsigned, n.d..; [1044]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified Baltimore newspaper (Box 18)
    Edgar Allan Poe, Jr., was honor guest at a dance given by his parents at the Baltimore Country Club.